this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hello this is Matthew Farwell
for software engineering radio today's
episode is about type driven development
with Edwin Brady Edwin is a lecturer in
computer science at the University of
st. Andrews interested in type theory
dependently typed functional programming
compilers and domain-specific languages
he is working on the implementation of
domain-specific languages for stateful
resource aware programming especially
for correct Network protocol design and
implementation using interests and
dependently typed functional programming
language Edwin welcome to software
engineering radio is there anything from
the bio that I've missed that's all
right chief ok so today we're going to
talk about type driven development using
interests I've already mentioned a
number of items which need defining and
I'd like to work through them let's
start with an easy one what is it type
ah
now if you ask a hundred computer
scientists so programmers the definition
of type you'll probably get at least a
hundred answers so I like to think of a
type as a way of classifying expressions
that is all of the expressions that are
integers all of the expressions that are
strings all of the expressions are lists
and so on just a way of saying what
something is giving giving a program
meaning ok is it is it documentation to
some extent it could be so there's lots
of ways you could view type so it's a
one one thing I like to think of the
type of being like a plan for what the
program is going to be a plan for what
we're going to do so typically what
happens when you write a program in your
favorite programming language let's say
your favorite compiled statically types
programming language what happens is you
write your program and then
almost every time the compiler says
you've done it wrong there's a type
error but I like to think of a type as
being a thing you can say to the machine
up front this is what we're going to
work on even if it is something as
simple as saying I am going to give you
a list and you're you are going to give
me back another list so the input to the
to a function is a list and the output
is a list even something as simple as
that
it's like saying what the program is
going to do before you before you
implement it okay so what when you said
statically typed a language what did you
mean by that right so when we talk of
sort of static and dynamic so kind of
phases of what happens to a program so
when we talk of static types or static
anything we're talking about things that
happen at compile time when when the
program is being everything that happens
before the program is run as dynamically
typed this is everything that happens
while the program is being run so we
talked of static types that basically
means we are checking that all of the
types in a program are consistent before
we run it so so there's not going to be
any type errors at runtime okay and what
is a type system so type system is
essentially the way the program or your
programming language checks that types
are being used or values are being used
in a consistent way so there are formal
definitions for the type system is but I
think the way to understand it is just
the way of programming language
manipulates values and ensures that they
use consistently do you have an example
of a statically typed language as
opposed to a dynamically typed language
well a statically typed language would
be for example Java Scala C was a
dynamically typed language would be Perl
Python Ruby I mean there's there's
something of a spectrum here in that all
of those languages I listed as
statically typed there there's still a
certain amount of
oceans and and manipulation of types
that can go on at runtime so for example
it's possible to write a Java program
where you are checking the types of
being used consistently at runtime but
there is a certain amount of checking
going on before the program is run like
if you you're not going to be able to to
send an INT to a method that's expecting
a string for example and I've heard
about strongly typed languages and
weakly typed languages yeah now I've
I've never been happy with either of
those terms because clearly there's any
clear formal definitions of what it
means to be strongly typed or weakly
types I can tell you how I understand
those terms and other people's
understanding will probably be very
different but the way I would understand
those terms is so that a weakly weakly
typed language is one where you can do
various conversions between types at
runtime and the machine won't know that
the language won't necessarily care
about whether those conversions are
correct or not so for example in C what
you can do is cast pretty much anything
to a point it to avoid and the machine
will quite happily let you do that
little thing if this goes wrong it's
your own fault I'm going to let you do
it whereas in a strongly typed language
any coercion is is is going to be
checked and it's going to be something
that the Machine makes sure there is
done correctly but I don't really like
either of those terms to be honest
because I find them essentially
meaningless because people's
understanding of them is just so
different do we need to make a
distinction in a language between
explicit typing and inferred typing
quite a kind of works I think so when
you when you say inferred typing is
you're talking about I not needing
necessarily to say what the type of a
variable is before you use it but the
machine will nevertheless know at
compile time what the type of that
variable or function is now in Haskell
for example Haskell is I didn't mention
that in my list of statically typed
languages which is
misses me is a functional programmer but
there you go Haskell a statically typed
functional language it is at least if
you stick to the Haskell 98 standard you
will never need to say what the type of
anything is at compile time the machine
will figure it out for you but you
mentioned explicitly typed languages so
if you if you don't write down the type
of anything if you don't write down the
types of any of your variables and yes
the machine can figure it out but you're
not necessarily helping yourself as a
programmer you're not you're not really
saying upfront what this program is
supposed to do it's kind of like if we
go back to my initial comment that's
types seeing types as a plan for a
program it's like saying okay
having having full type inference is
saying okay here's what we did what was
it we were actually planning to do so
the type is like okay but the Machine
says right this is this is what you just
did is that what you meant whereas
having an explicit type is is saying
this is what we're going to do can you
check that I've that is really what
we've done but in practice and I like to
have a mix between the two I like to say
sort of at the top level I like to give
a type to a function and then within
that function yes I'll be creating lots
of variables using lots of helper
functions and so on and I don't
necessarily want to give types to those
but I do want to put a type at the top
to say this is what my plan is in that
in my experience types documentation
like you say yes so it's sort of saying
this is what the plan was this is this
is what we intended to do and you as a
user of this library or a user of this
API at least you know what it was we
were planning to do with this with this
function so it's it's some people take
this idea to extremes I mean you did
again you often hear this from people
right right there Haskell libraries I
think a wonderful library to do all
kinds of sophisticated things but
they're they're a little short on
documentation this isn't I mean this is
no universal comment I'm being a bit
unfair on some library authors in saying
this but you're very often people will
write their libraries and
they say the types other documentation
you can figure out what this library is
going to do from the types well not
really you still need a little bit of
guidance like maybe you need an overview
of how the library works maybe you need
it a synopsis of a kind of a sort of
canonical way of using the library and
at that point once you've got the
general idea that I find the types can
be really useful at the documentation
there's documentation but they are not a
substitute for documentation okay it
assumes that you're using the same words
to mean the same things as well for
example okay so what are dependent types
right so actually slightly prefer the
phrase first-class types these days so
when we introduce functional programming
when we use functional languages we talk
of we often talk of functions being a
first-class or a function is a
first-class construct of the language so
a first-class construct being one where
you can assign it to variables pass it
to functions return it from functions
and so on so in a functional language
you can assign functions to variables
you can pass functions to functions and
so on so first-class types allow you to
do the same sort of thing with types so
we can as we can pass types to functions
we can return types from functions we
can assign types of variables and so on
and what this means is we can write
functions which calculate types from
some input so this is why we call them
dependent types this is why that's our
technical term is dependent types is
that you can have a type that depends on
some other value so I'll give a concrete
example I'll give two concrete examples
in fact the first one I'll give is lists
so in a in a conventional statically
typed language with generics say you
might be able to say that the append
function takes a list of type X and
another list of type X and it returns a
list of type X so that is at least
guaranteeing that you get a list back
with the same element type as the inputs
were so if you then have this ability to
calculate
types from values you can start say
things like for a repent function where
we have a list of type X of length n a
list of type X of length M and it gives
us back a list of type X of length n
plus M so it's giving us additional
guarantees it says more about it we're
talking about plans again says more
about what the plan for the program is
that our plan really is to produce a
list that is that whose length is the
sum of the input lists and and it gives
us this guarantee that you know it's not
going to return an empty list or it's
not going to return something something
meaningless in terms of lengths that's
the first example that's that's kind of
the canonical example that people always
give first in the dependent type but
there's one that I think more
experienced software developers will
will be very familiar with which is
printf so printf in C where you have a
format string and that format string
tells you what the types of the next
arguments are going to be a printf % s %
d is going to say well now we're taking
a string and an int so that really the
the type of printf if you were able to
write it down precisely improperly in C
would it would have a dependent type
because that first argument the format
string is calculating is being used to
calculate the type of the rest of the
function ok so just so just so I
understand this I have a function printf
which takes one argument which is the
the format string and then that
calculates another function which takes
multiple types depending on the value
that you give it for the format string
you mentioned Java generics they aren't
dependent types they aren't there so you
could argue I suppose that they are but
they are types that can only depend on
other types that can only be constructed
by by building up other types and I
think I did recently see something that
was showing that that Java generics
turn out to be cheering complete III
forget where I saw that which means you
probably could do something horrific
that would that would that would allow
you to express very precisely in Java
types and what a function is supposed to
do but you know in in in in the most
common use case I would say they're not
dependent types they give you a bit more
precision than your ordinary Java types
without generics they allow you to
express more precisely that you know the
input has the same element type is the
output but it's hard work to go much
further than that our units a good
example of dependent type so to be not
in physical unit is form units meters
per second yes Oh meters so so f sharp
has this kind of unit of measure and
yeah in a sense they out because what's
happening is you have you know inputs
let's say you're calculating the speed
and you've got distance in meters and
the time in seconds then the output of
that function the appetite for that
function is something that you're going
to be able to compute from the types of
the input so an input type in meters and
input type in seconds so yes to some
extent you're certainly getting more
precision for your types if you're able
to express units of measure and you know
as far as I'm concerned any any way and
any type system that allows you to be
more precise in advance about what a
function is supposed to do or what a
method is supposed to do has got to be a
good thing
so I mean unit of measure is quite a
nice example because there there have
been genuine examples of software
failures caused by unit errors I mean
the classic one is this is the mass
climate orbiter yes where sent to Mars
in 1999 the intention to be to
communicate with the Polar Lander and
what I actually did was crash straight
into Mars because there was no moon
where that a mismatch between the using
imperial units on ground-based software
and metric units on the on the
spacecraft itself
you know it's it's when we're writing
programs and we get something wrong you
know we just start it again we can turn
the computer off and on again it it's a
bit harder if it's taken six months to
get to Mars so 15 years to blown your
thing except exactly so a bit I don't
think they've made that mistake again
it's not a mistake you make twice so
you've mentioned some of the advantages
of dependent types or first-class types
could you say some other ones so thing
I'm working on at the minute is dealing
with state so stateful systems so at the
end of the day any program you're going
to write that is going to be used in
practice is going to have to deal with
the outside world it's going to have to
manipulate external entities you know
user inputs file handles network sockets
that sort of thing
so typically api's tell you in in there
types they tell you what things are so
what the inputs and outputs to a
function are but they don't tell you
anything about when you can use them so
for example if you if you're trying to
write to a file there's a your API will
typically provide you with something
that you know takes a file handle in a
string and it will write that write the
string to that file but what if that
file handle isn't open or what if what
if it failed to open because the disk is
full so what I mean so you've mentioned
this in my bio as well talking about the
main specific languages and and stay
tuned resource aware systems what you
can do if you have more precision in
your type system is it starts saying
right I can only I can only do that
right to a file if I have successfully
opened the file so the file is not only
there's not only only a handle that says
what this what this file is it also
tells us what state that file handle is
currently in so after I've closed a file
for example I shouldn't be able to write
to it and I shouldn't be able to read
from it if I only opened it for writing
and so on so I think this is starting
this is um this is even more useful than
things we talked about with you know
lengths and and printf because these
these are the kinds of pro
to come up day-to-day in programming
latina
trying trying to use a resource that you
don't currently have access to and
there's even though there's even a
fairly recent example of this kind of
problem in the wild so you remember um
apples go to fail error so this was an
error in TLS implementation where there
were two lines of C code that were go to
fail so essentially what was happening
there is there was a protocol that was
being followed a series of state
transitions that were being followed and
because there were two lines saying go
to fail and the second one was always
being followed because of the prices
missing this meant that the protocol
wasn't being followed in the way that it
was supposed to be so you have a state
transition system you have things that
are supposed to happen when the system
is in a certain state but that's not
happening because there's been a
programming error so precise types allow
you to express that sort of thing
dependent types allow you to express
that sort of thing in your API to make
sure that that kind of error gets caught
at compile time
now I I'm not saying that you know had
had had have Apple implemented there you
know TLS implementation in Idris
everything would have been fine because
of course as a whole there's a whole
load of other things they would have to
do but that kind of that kind of extra
position in your type system I think
will really help us to get to avoid this
kind of security issue okay so you
mentioned Idris could you give us a
brief overview of interests and why
you'd created it yes so address is a
functional programming language that is
based around this idea of type driven
development and dependent types so I
created it because I've been working on
I've been I've been researching
dependent types as a programming
language constructs how we could use
them how we could even implement them
how can we how we could compile them
efficiently for a number of years and it
was it was disappointing to me in all of
this time that there wasn't really any
no I thought that you know this these
ideas were really cool there wasn't
really any kind of system where a
software developer could could
reasonably pick
up and start implementing the sort of
programs that they would care about
there was the systems that we had in
existence are really good for proving
mathematical properties so there's the
system called which built creative
inria in in in France and you do all
kinds of amazing things with it proving
all kinds of amazing properties of
software proving all kinds of
mathematical properties but I didn't
feel that you could look at a
program and kind of understand what it
was doing and feel you could write it
yourself so Idris is really an attempt
to make these ideas of precise types and
software verification accessible to
software developers you know people
people who actually know how to write
programs that do useful things you know
I don't know how to write programs to do
useful things I doesn't know how to make
programming languages but I would only
like to make a programming language that
people but people can use to to do
useful things and that means sort of
thinking carefully about notation
thinking carefully about where you need
to expose details of the kind of formal
verification of properties and where you
can just hide them away because that can
be taken care of for the program so
thinking very carefully about notation
and readability okay so does that mean
that what you saying about before about
first-class types that's usable in
address and for instance can you connect
pass a type to a function and what would
I what would what advantages does that
give me so passing a type to your
function is it's kind of like generic
programming in that you're passing a
type to say what the element type of a
list is going to be I think more
interestingly is when you can when you
can calculate a type and return it from
the front of a function so so if you if
you pass in a value say there's no like
for the printf well say for the printf
yeah so so you'll put you pass in the
form a string and you get back the type
of the printf function or pass in a
description of a database schema and you
get back a type that says how you query
schemer or you pass in pass in the
length of the the content length of an
HTTP request and you read the correct
number of bytes on on the socket that
kind of thing could you explain to me
the difference so I come from a Java
background I can do reflection on types
so I pass an object into a function and
I can say that object is a string or
it's an integer or whatever it is what
what's the difference between that and a
function I pass it type into a function
so when you when you talk of reflection
this is something that's happening at
runtime yeah yes the the difference
really is that this is all happening at
compile time and because it's happening
at compile time
there's a guarantee that every time you
run this program no matter what data
shows up it will be used consistently
incorrectly there won't be any there
won't be any runtime errors it won't be
used inconsistently not only that but
because it's being used at compile time
and I think this is this is far more
important than the B correctness side of
things and the runtime errors sort of
things because we've got this
information at compile time the compiler
can use that information or the type
checker can use that information to
guide you towards writing the right
program okay so so there's a concept I
haven't mentioned yet is holes the idea
of holes in in address we in type driven
development we don't typically write a
complete program and feed that to the
compiler we write as much of the program
as we as we want to so we might writers
or skeleton structure of a program but
leave holes for the bits of the program
we haven't written yet and if you then
ask the Machine to tell you about the
type of that hole
it will tell you what you have available
and what type you need to complete the
program so it means if you are doing
this kind of reflection on values that
show up at runtime you can nevertheless
reason about them at compile time and
the Machine will tell you what you need
to do to finish writing the program so
this is this is all coming back to types
as a plan for the program
so if you say to them if you write the
type first and the type is then the plan
for what you're going to do the machine
can tell you more about what it is you
need to do next so we're moving as much
as possible from runtime to compile time
so people you hear people say things
like you know static types where
possible dynamic types were necessary
well I'm just trying to move that that
boundary to make more things possible at
the end of the day you are gonna have to
do dynamic checking at some point
because users will provide all kinds of
nonsense when they're using your program
but the more you can do a compile time
the more you can be sure that the things
that do turn up are dealt with properly
so if I'm doing a lot of this let's call
it computation at compile time does that
mean we have to have we have problems
with you know for instance the halting
problem and you have to be careful about
what you're doing and your compiler can
go on for years and years well so that
the compiler can go on for ages and ages
and ages and whether whether the the
halting problem is there or not because
you might have a program that halts but
it you know when is it enough so this is
certainly potentially a problem and and
you've got to you've got to use some
care in how you write down your types so
it's you you you can't simply say right
I'm gonna write down a really
complicated type and this type is going
to prove everything and everything is
going to be fine because the program is
going to type check well it doesn't
really work as as easily as death
unfortunately I mean you're generally
better off writing you know starting off
with a fairly simple type and just
refining it as necessary as as you learn
more about your problem I should say
something about the halting problem
because it is a it is a very valid point
so the fact that we can calculate types
means that we are evaluating functions
we're running programs to calculate
those types and if those programs don't
halt the problem is that your compiler
doesn't halt mm-hmm so two things we do
firstly we make sure we have a totality
checker so totality checking is looking
at a program and seeing if it will
always produce a result in finite time
now because of the halting problem this
is
we're not always gonna get an answer to
this but there is a fragment where we
can say yes this program definitely
halts and then the rest of them we say
well the totality checker says it's
either yes or I don't know it will never
actually say no and Idris will only
evaluate things at compile time if it's
certain that they are going to halt in
practice it's if you're writing programs
in types that don't obviously halt I
think you've made things far too
complicated and you know it's if you
have a very complicated type how do you
know that you've got the right type so
yes we have a lot of power in the type
system we have a lot of power to express
what programs are supposed to do but we
still need to be careful that we know
keep the types understandable so my my
recommendation so we have this photo
allottee checker
we have the ability to you know tell if
programs are going to produce a result
in finite time and there's a deal to
that which is that we can tell whether a
program is going to be productive so if
you're writing a server for example what
you're going to do or what you're hoping
to do is guarantee that your program
will run forever but produce some new
result every so often at least so it
it'll it'll it'll produce a read it will
always terminate when responding to a
request and it will respond to requests
forever so that would be a total program
so what I well I strongly recommend when
when writing interest programs is to aim
to make those programs total and what
you should do with your types is start
with the simplest type possible the
simplest type that that expresses your
initial understanding of the problem and
as you learn more about the problem just
try to make that type precise enough
that it gives you more help in showing
that your program is total okay so you
start off with the types rather than the
let's call it business logic the logic
of the program yeah and and as you as
you develop the business logic you'll
probably learn a little bit more about
what the reasonable inputs to your
program are and you might you might be
able to refine your type slightly to to
rule out certain inputs and say okay I
want to rule out these inputs at compile
time I can give you a ridiculously
simple 870 minutes so really is
ridiculously simple imagine we are
writing our business logic we've we've
set up a business to calculate the tail
of a lists the tail of a linked list so
we try writing a program that says ok if
the list is non-empty we'll remove the
first element from list and there's our
tail what if the list is empty well hang
on to that that's not meaningful anymore
so what we do is say ok we're not going
to use we're going to refine our model
of the problem to be from from being
lists to being lists of at least one
element ok so so you know when we
started writing that program yes we
thought we were going to be able to do
it for all lists we very quickly
realized that there's certain lists that
this program doesn't make sense for so
we refine the type slightly so we have a
new type which is of type list of length
n plus 1 ok ok so the input type is list
of length n plus 1 the output type is a
list of length n ok and then whereas
before the input type was less the
appetite was list ok now see that's a
ridiculously simple example but you see
this sort of thing cropping up in
largest go problems where you say ok
I'll I'll come up with some model for
the inputs that I might get but it
actually turns out some of those models
are meaningless because maybe there's
maybe that's too bit of data that never
makes sense to come in together so long
we find the time to make that not
possible this podcast is supported by
atlanticnet posting solution provider of
healthcare HIPAA PCI compliance and AD
tech if you're feeling the pain of
having outdated technology call
atlanticnet and get the latest security
firewall intrusion detection backup
disaster recovery and virtualization or
if you're starting a new project or not
getting the results you want from your
current providers atlanticnet can help
you succeed
the fully audited solutions in 23 years
in business they won't let you down
visit atlanticnet to learn more okay so
on that theme in the book the the type
driven development book you talk about
protocol could you explain quickly what
protocol is and what you mean by
protocol and what you how you model it
using address so I think if I remember
rightly the first one I do is modeling a
door where you've got a door which has
two States open and closed and there's
three operations ring the bell open the
door one close the door so when I talk
of protocols this is like a resource
usage protocol where our resource is the
door and there are operations we can do
on a door but some of them that are only
valid at certain types so it doesn't
make sense to open the door if it's
already open doesn't make sense to close
the door already closed so a correct a
correct usage of that resource would be
to ring the bell open the door then
close the door so when I talk of
protocols basically what I'm saying is
what what order you have to do
operations in what order it's meaningful
to do operations it and that that could
be that could be fairly constrained or
it could be it could be fairly free but
you are at least saying that things can
only happen when your resource is in a
certain state so yeah really really
talking about when you can do things or
when you can run operations rather than
simply what operations can you do and
what inputs and outputs do they do they
take and how would I would I model that
with start modeling that with address so
what I typically do is you know go back
to computer science 101 and start
drawing the the finite state machine so
there's another example from the book
actually that might be a more realistic
one the bite might might be illustrative
here so let's say let's say we're making
an ATM for a bank so we might think
about what what are the one of the
security properties of that ATM that we
are worried about both as a customer and
as the bank so as the bank we want to
make sure that the Machine only
dispenses money if it's got into a state
where the customer has proved that they
they are entitled to access that money
and as a customer we want to be sure
that someone else can't just take our
card and put it in the machine and it'll
just work so so we can think about the
the states the state that we need to get
into for the machine to safety dispensed
money we say right we have to somehow
arrive at a state where the customer has
inserted their card and they validated
their PIN so we've already got three
states that we need to think about we've
got the machine is just sitting there
idling just sitting there on the street
waiting for a card to be inserted we've
got the state where the card is in but
the pin hasn't been entered yet and
we've got the state where we're in a
session interacting with our bank
account so then we think about okay how
do we get between those states we can
get into the card inserted state by
inserting a card we can get into the we
have a session with the bank state by
entering a pin and having the Machine
verified that that pin was successful so
now we're starting to starting to write
down operations and establish under what
circumstances it's okay to be running
those operations so we can draw a
picture of this just with arrows saying
what the operations are and when those
operations are valid and then how we
kept between them once you have that
it's a matter of writing down the type
that expresses the input state the
output state and whether whether we
successfully got between the input state
in the output state so you have one type
per state basically one type per state
machine per state machine yes oh so this
is the state machine here is we've got
we'll call it idle card inserted and
sessions we've got three states sir and
we can put those three three states into
one type which would call let's call it
ATM state and then our operations on the
state machine are going to be so the
types are going to be calculated from
those states so a so earlier we had you
know list of list of length n well here
we have machine in state ID machine in
state validated so this is a this is a
pattern that that you see very often
when working with when working with
external resources you have operations
with preconditions you have operations
with post conditions and we can
guarantee at compile time that when we
when we execute an operation the machine
was in the state that it had to be in
for that operation to to work okay so
let's talk about instead of talking
about protocols can we talk about
concurrency
yeah pleasingly it turns out to be
pretty much the same thing but a bit
more complicated so I mean what I've
tried to do in the book is is is present
the basic idea so that you can you you
can see the absolute fundamentals of
what's going on and then start thinking
about how to scale it up so what's
happening with currency let's let's
think about message passing concurrency
so so so this is some axel model where
where you have processors are
communicating with each other
essentially by sending messages back and
forth so what you really want to make
sure is that all of the processes in
your concurrent system are working to
the same script so if one process is
expecting to receive a message that says
I mean let's let's say processes running
some kind of server that's doing
arithmetic operations so so that process
is sitting there expecting messages of
the form add two and three and then it
will send a reply of the form in this
case five so if something is sending a
message to that process then it has to
know what the appropriate type of that
message is and it has to know that after
it sent the message the next thing it's
going to get there the next thing is
going to do
is receive a reply of the right form so
we're in a state machine kind of system
again where the states are haven't sent
a message yet have sent a message have
received a reply okay and and then the
corresponding state machine for the
other process is haven't received a
message yet have received a message have
sent a reply so what you have to do a
bit more complicated here because when
you when you spawn the thread you have
to kind of generate two corresponding
state transition systems for the two
processes and then those two processes
as you write the program they can do
what they like in general but when it
comes to sending messages it had better
be in the right order so the neat thing
here is that you can because because we
can calculate types we can start writing
programs which Express concurrent
protocols and then generate the
appropriate state transition systems as
needed by any specific program okay now
it's cool so this this is a little bit
beyond the scope of where the book got
to but it's something I've been working
on recently and what's been really quite
pleasing is that yeah I kind of
suspected it was going to be the same
thing and it's always nice when you
suspect something is going to be the
same as something that was a bit easier
and then it actually is that's always
lovely so hopefully there'll be more to
be said on that in there in the coming
weeks book - book - one thing I've
learned about writing a book who knows
certainly enough coming papers and
tutorials I'll be I'll be writing about
that just for the listeners we've had
software engineering radio episodes on
the actor model before notably episode 2
49 which is Vaughn Vernon or reactive
programming with the actor model so if
they want to have a look at that that's
available on the site so I just like to
move on now to type driven development
we've mentioned it in passing but could
we dig a bit deeper now could you
explain the basic thrust of type
development so so it all comes back to
this idea of types being the plan and
the machine the Machine being there to
help you not the Machine being there to
tell you off so it's you
you also get into the habit of
deliberately writing programs that you
know aren't going to type-check because
you want the machine to give you more
information about about where you are
and what you need to do and deliberately
writing programs that aren't complete
with with this idea of holes so the
rhythm of programming type driven
development is write down a type so just
come up with some definition of the
model in which you're working so like it
might be it might be your initial idea
of what the state machine is sorry not
in our ATM example just what are what
what do we think the state of that ATM
are so step one is type write down a
type then try defining a function trying
to try to you know pick your first
function that you want to want to
implement define it when you define it
you will probably not write the thing in
one go
so again think of our ATM example the
first thing that happens might be we
respond to the user inserting their card
but then we leave a hole we say okay
what I'm just gonna make sure that it
type checks so far and then ask the
machine while I'm supposed to do next so
so write down a type then come up with a
definition and then refine the
definition all the time making sure that
it's still type checks and eventually
we'll hopefully get to a point where the
program is complete and type checks so
we've kind of got it down into three
steps we've got to have a I was told by
this basically came up with this while
writing the book the editor told me that
you have to have a three word pithy
mantra for a for a development
methodology because you know test-driven
development has red green refactor so
okay we have type define refine this is
what you're thinking of it's it how do i
model the problem in a type how do i
define a function that manipulates that
type and then refine it is your
understanding of the problem and your
understanding of the model develops and
this is this is all of these steps will
will will feed back into the other
but the essence of it is types come
first types or a plan for the program
and it's okay to write incomplete
programs and ask the Machine what you
need to do next so the very interactive
so it's very much a conversation with
with the programming language rather
than a needle feeding feeding your
recipe to the feeding your feeding your
request to the Oracle and see if it's
denied or accepted
so can we drill down a little bit more
into that so let's let's take our
example of the ATM machine I come up
with the type which is card inserted and
I want to be able to take some and say
the user can take some money out now so
I'd like to go a bit more of a concrete
example here can we drill down on the
ATM machines so a customer comes up and
inserts their card into the ATM machine
has to enter their pin could we just
have a more of a concrete feel about how
the development process how the
development process works with that
specific example please okay so let's
assume that we've come up with the type
for this where we've got we've worked
out the state machine we've worked out
the state transitions that it insert the
cards get yourself into the session by
entering your PIN correctly and then
once you've finished take the card out
the machine is idling again so what we
need to think about is what is the
overall type for for this interaction so
our ATM our implementation of this ATM
it has an input state in an output state
so kind of a precondition on the
operations and a post condition what
happens after the operations so a
complete cycle of using this ATM is
going to start in the idle state and
it's going to finish in the idle State
so a top-level type might look something
like ATM program that's what we call it
and it has type ATM of idle idle so
we're just we've got the input state in
the output state in the type so the type
is ATM idle idle so we're going to do a
sequence of operations the first thing
that's going to have
than is we let's say we have a command
that basically sits there waiting for a
card to be inserted so let's call that
command insert card for the sake of
argument so what's the type of insert
card well it has to express that it
takes the machine from the idle state to
the card inserted state so I'll write
the first line of this program which is
just insert card and then I'll leave a
hole for the rest of the program and if
I look at the type of that hole it will
tell me that whereas before the thing we
were trying to write how to type ATM
idle idle where the input state is idle
output state is idle now we'll see that
the stator that the type of the program
we need to write is a program that takes
an ATM from the card inserted state back
to the idle state so by looking at that
hole we see what the state of the system
is now it's like the abstract state of
the system that there is a card in it
and somehow we have to write a sequence
of operations that gets us back into the
idle state so we've got a variety of
other commands at our disposal we've got
we've got things like we've got commands
like prompt for pin
we've got of command for checking the
pin we've got a command for ejecting the
card we've got a command for dispensing
the money so of all of those commands we
have available of all of those commands
that we've defined in our API the only
ones were allowed to use at this point
are the ones which are valid with the
precondition of a card being inserted so
by looking at the type of the hole we
see what state were in by looking at the
type of the operations we see what road
we're allowed to use so for example the
dispense money command is not valid in
this state so even though it's part of
our API even though it's part of our and
if you're thinking in an object-oriented
sense we might imagine defining an
object for our ATM or defining a class
for our ATM which has all these things
as methods but we can't clearly define
at compile time which of these methods
were allowed to use not easily okay
we'll say okay the cards inserted now
what do we do well probably good idea to
is to prompt for a pin and then check
the pin so when we check the pin well
what that does is go
to depend on whether the pin was entered
correctly so either it's going to move
the machine into the running session
state or it's going to keep the machine
in the card inserted state so what we'll
do is check the pin and it will return
the value and somehow this is easier to
do with it with a text editor in front I
guess I guess our medium is send so we
will have to just have to imagine this
so the interesting thing we'd see if we
had if we had this on the machine in
front of us let's say that get pinned
has returned a value of type boolean and
it's called the variable is called
success okay sorry if success is true
then we move into the running session
state if success is false we're in the
card inserted State but if we look at
that if we just if we just assign the
result of check pin to the variable
success and we now look at the state of
the machine the machine will tell us
that the current state is if success
then running session else card inserted
okay so that state that that's that we
can't do anything in that state because
we don't actually know what state we're
in until we've checked that that value
of that variable so essentially what the
type is doing here is it's telling us
exactly what we have to do in order to
make progress on this problem it says
you cannot make progress on this problem
until you've bothered to check whether
that result was successful and does
interest help you with this process
Idris will tell you exactly what to do
in that situation because it will give
you if you write if you write down these
types of this operation it will tell you
that the current state of the machine is
unresolved until you check the until you
check the result of that operation so
it's like when you if you open a file in
C it will succeed or not you might get a
null pointer or not but you can just
blunder on as if that file opened
successfully even if it didn't really
what you should be doing is checking the
return value of the function to see if
it was successful or not because the
system is in a different state depending
on what the return value is that
function is because we've set up in our
ATM example because we've set up the
types in such a way that say this
is an abstraction of the state is in the
type and I'm not going to tell you
whether you're in the successful or did
the the running session State or the
card inserted state until you've checked
this return value you've got additional
information a compile time and make sure
you get that program right okay so how
do we express things that we don't know
can we express things that we don't know
so we write functions so this is this is
what I think is really neat about having
first class types anything you would
write in a program you can put in a type
so if you want to I mean if you're
running a program and and you want to
make some decision based on what happens
at runtime what do you do well you write
a function that makes a decision based
on the thing that happens at runtime so
what we could do is put that kind of
function in the type and it will maybe
it will be calculated from some variable
and that variable might not be known
until runtime but at least we can reason
about it at compile time we can say okay
under the assumption that success equals
true well if if we are assuming that
success equals true we can now run that
function we can we can run that function
that works based on the result of of the
operation so we're saying that if if
this value happens to have if this
variable happens to have the value true
at run time we're just going to write
this branch of the code under the
assumption that this this variable was
true and because because they're just
ordinary functions you don't have to do
any kind of you know tricky type level
gymnastics you just write the function
and the same function that's running at
compile time is the thing that's going
to run at runtime and it allows us to do
a lot more some analysis but most
importantly it allows the machine to
tell us what we need to do in order to
make progress on our specific problem I
mean this is really what type driven
development is all about it is is
setting up the types so that the machine
can help you out okay moving towards
wrapping up now just a quick question on
the history why up until now haven't
languages had this sort of functionality
why haven't they had dependent types why
haven't they I guess lots of reasons
but I have found that dependent types
work an awful lot better in a pure
functional setting so I could just you
know move that to another question of
why haven't functional programming
languages taken off yet okay maybe this
is maybe this isn't the place to answer
this question but in the end I don't see
why I don't see why we can't have
imperative languages which have full
dependent types there's there's a
certain amount of difficulty in that you
have to be you have to be in this pure
fragment that allows you to run programs
at compile time because I certainly
don't want to be running let's say that
I am writing a program which which
deletes a file under some circumstances
that is really something I don't want to
be running a compile time I shouldn't be
right I shouldn't be doing I shouldn't
be running something that that has side
effects at compile time but I would like
to be able to run things run run
functions which you know which are just
pure expressions at compile time they
allow me to reason about abstract state
of the system at compile time so I would
I would hope to see that over the coming
years that you know as a you know I mean
I'm I'm an academic I'm not really here
to sell my language to to the next you
know big industry I don't have the
resources to do that
you know I but if if you know Google or
Facebook or whatever come along and
they're going to make their next big
language I would love them to take the
ideas that we've got steal our ideas
from you know having having compile time
evaluation of expressions and think how
can we put that into a into a more
mainstream may be imperative maybe
object-oriented may be purely functional
language so you don't want to see
address being used in the next Mars
Lander if it is going to be used in the
next Mars Lander I would hope that the
people who do that have enough resources
to throw at it to make it more robust
make it more efficient to really
properly audit the runtime system
there's a lot of that there's a lot of
things beyond the type system that
you're gonna have to do to make the to
make the system really production ready
for that kind of environment but you
know my my business really
and providing ideas for the people who
do have those resources to to be able to
do things so you'd like you'd like to
see it in scholar or in her scale so
it's it's tricky in in Haskell and
scarlet for example you have this clear
distinction between what is a type and
what is a value and just historically
that's that's that's the way the
language is once you have that
distinction it's very hard to remove it
and how things still work the way they
used to because you know you still have
to have your standard Haskell programs
working your standard scarlet programs
working so being able to introduce full
dependent types at the same time as
having everything else still work it's
going to be a little bit challenging I
think if we're gonna have a mainstream
language with dependent types it's going
to have to be a new language so not
Haskell not Scala
not interest it's got to be something
that's designed from the ground up to be
that kind of language and I don't see
any reason why it why why it can't be
that way other than somebody's got to do
it well there's still a lot to work out
I mean there's give what is what is the
right core language to have what is what
is what is the most efficient way of
implementing the kinds of tricks you
need to do at the type level so I think
there's still a lot of research to be
done before this is a truly mainstream
way of writing programs but you know
we're having lots of fun figuring these
things out so as far as I'm concerned
that's what matters okay the last
question that I have is why why is it
called interests ah no there's a long
answer to this in the short one I'll
give you the short one first and you can
edit out the long so the short answer is
well it just sounds like a programming
language name doesn't this it has a nice
ring to it the long answer is something
I think is only comprehensible by by
British people of of the right sort of
age so do you remember either the end
yes yeah so there's a dragon in either
the engine a singing dragon called Idris
and I had one of my early experiments in
implementing dependent types was a was a
theorem proving engine
and so essentially it did all the core
things that you needed to use type
theory to prove interesting mathematical
properties and I was about to submit it
to a conference and I didn't have a name
for it and I was just thinking well it's
an engine so what engines are there well
there's Thomas Thomas isn't the theorem
prover named Ivor that sounds like a
serum proven eh that'll do
and then the first implementation of
Idris was just built from some of the
components of Ivor
so interests the dragon in the book
hatched out of hatched in Ivor's boiler
Idris the programming language pretty
much did the same thing yeah so there
you go you've probably have to edit that
out of us well I have heard his name dr.
interest Alba absolutely nothing to do
with Idris Elba I hadn't even heard of a
Drizella but when I cool is there
anything else I should have asked you
that's a good question I can't think of
anything that I would have a burning
desire to talk about that I that I
haven't okay
my current hobbyhorses is the state
machines and all of that so it's good to
get that in and how can listeners find
out more about interests so the easiest
thing to do is go to Idris Lang org
that's it ris - lamda org if you look at
it it's you'll see that it has very much
the luck of a website created by an
academic so you know if we have any any
web designers who would who are
desperate to to make it look shinier
that would be lovely
you can also go onto Twitter there's an
account idris lang on twitter that's all
one word and time driven development
so type driven development with idris
recently published by manning like
tinyurl.com slash type DD will take you
to the the manning page on that okay and
what about you and you if you if you
follow if you follow a link there's
there's a couple of articles linked from
there and you'll find a discount code in
those things okay so if
and yeah you can find me on Twitter as
well so Edwin Brady on Twitter that's
brilliant
okay well thank you for joining us today
Edwin that's thank you for having me
this is Matthew Farwell for software
engineering radio thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by Triple E software magazine for
more about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website @ SC - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com
you can also email us at team @ SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
SU radio is licensed under creative
commons license' two-point-five thanks
for listening